Guide to the Ernest Sturm Collection, approximately 1700-1925
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Ernest Sturm Collection
approximately 1700-1925
Sturm, Ernest
2 cubic feet (4 boxes and 6 volumes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Variety of rare manuscripts relating to American and European history, art and literature. Also includes an 18th century manuscript of the Koran.
Scope and Content Note
Includes an original typescript of Woodrow Wilson on the States and the federal government, a letter and maps relating to the battle of Gettysburg; documents and letters signed by members of George Washington's first cabinet; documents relating to the Revolutionary Battle of Harlem Heights; documents signed by Catherine the Great relating to the Russian Navy; letters and documents signed by signers of the Declaration of Independence; items signed by American naval figures; a signed card and portraits of William Tecumseh Sherman; items signed by Napoleon Bonaparte, his family and generals; photos, letters, and documents relating to the Civil War; similar items of English literary and artistic figures; a letter of Edmund Burke; a letter and photos of Robert Browning; a letter of Robert E. Lee; printed copy of the United States Constitution dated 1787; letters and documents signed by American Presidents; transcript of a poem by Robert Louis Stevenson, and eighteenth century manuscripts copy of the Koran.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Catherine II, Empress of Russian, 1729-1796; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891; Napoleon I, Emperor of the French, 1769-1821; Burke, Edmund, 1729-1797; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward). 1807-1870; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Stevenson, Robert Louis, 1850-1894
Subjects:
State governments; Manuscripts, Arabic; Authors, English; Artists--England; Presidents--United States; Generals--France
Places:
Russia. Voennyi flot; United States. Navy; United States, Declaration of Independence--signers; Gettysburg, Battle of, Gettysburg, Pa., 1863; Harlem Heights, Battle of, N.Y., 1776; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; United States--Politics and government--1789-1797; United States--History-Revolution, 1775-1783; France--History, Military; United States--Politics and government--1783-1789
Document Types:
Autographs; Photographs; Maps; Poems
Titles:
United States. Constitution
VCL Categories
Autographs; Literature and Writing; Politics
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, August 2007.
Custodial History
Collected by Ernest Sturm, father of Ruth Foster Sturm, VC 1932.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ruth Foster Sturm, 1997.
Series List
- Series I. Woodrow Wilson, (Box 1)
- Series II. Gettysburg, (Box 1)
- Series III. Washington's First Cabinet, (Box 1)
- Series IV. Battle of Harlem Heights, (Box 1)
- Series V. Catherine the Great, (volume 1)
- Series VI. Signers of the Declaration of Independence, (Box 3)
- Series VII. The American Navy, (Box 1)
- Series VIII. William Tecumseh Sherman, (Box 1)
- Series IX. Napoleon and His Generals, (Box 1)
- Series X. Civil War, (Box 2)
- Series XI. English Literature and Art, (Box 4)
- Series XII. Edmund Burke, (Box 4)
- Series XIII. Robert Browning, (Box 2)
- Series XIV. Robert E. Lee, (Box 2)
- Series XV. Constitution of The United States, (volume 2)
- Series XVI. Presidents of The United States, (volume 3)
- Series XVII. Robert Louis Stevenson, (volume 4)
- Series XVIII. Napoleon and His Family, (volume 5)
- Series XIX. Koran, (volume 6)
Container List
- Series I: Woodrow Wilson
  - The States and The Federal Government, [printed galleys] (Folder 1.1)
  - The States and The Federal Government, [signed typescript] (Folder 1.2)
- Series II: Gettysburg
  - Battle of Gettysburg Map, 1863 (Folder 1.3)
  - Eyewitness Account of the Battle of Gettysburg, 1863 (Folder 1.4)
  - Map of Pennsylvania Movement of Gibbons 2nd Army Corp, 1863 (Folder 1.5)
- Series III: Washington's First Cabinet
  - Hamilton, Alexander, 1794 (Folder 1.6)
  - Jefferson, Thomas, 1792 (Folder 1.7)
  - Randolph, Edmond, 1794 (Folder 1.8)
  - Washington, George — Appointment of M. de Poirey, 1790 (Folder 1.9)
- Series IV: Battle of Harlem Heights
  - Agreement of Massachusetts Minute Men, 17-- (Folder 1.10)
  - Hancock, John — Appointment of Josiah Hayden, 1781 (Folder 1.11)
  - Hayden, Josiah — account of the Battle of Harlem Heights, 1776 (Folder 1.12)
  - Order of the Committee of Safety On Enlistment of Men, 1775 (Folder 1.13)
- Series V: Catherine the Great
  - Collection of approximately 40 manuscript documents signed by Catherine, mostly relating to Russian Naval Matters, 1792-96. Bound in contemporary green velvet. Evidently removed from the Russian Royal Archive after the Revolution, 1792-1796 (Volume 1)
- Series VI: Signers of the Declaration of Independence
  - Adams, Samuel, 1774, 1795 (Folder 3.1)
  - Barlett, Josiah, 1776 (Folder 3.2)
  - Carroll, Charles, 1829 (Folder 3.3)
  - Clymer,George, 1803 (Folder 3.4)
  - Ellery, William, 1781 (Folder 3.5)
  - Franklin, Benjamin, 1777 (Folder 3.6)
  - Gerry, Elbridge, 1812 (Folder 3.7)
  - Hancock, John, 1758 (Folder 3.8)
  - Hart, John, 1742, 1776 (Folder 3.9)
  - Hopkins, Stephen, 1771 (Folder 3.10)
  - Hopkinson, Francis, 1790 (Folder 3.11)
  - Huntington, Samuel, 1780, 1789, 1793, 1812 (Folder 3.12)
  - Jefferson, Thomas, 1807 (Folder 3.13)
  - McKean, Thomas, 1768, 1780, 1816, 1849 (Folder 3.14)
  - Middleton, Arthur, 1762 (Folder 3.15)
  - Morris, Robert, 1782, 1798 (Folder 3.16)
  - Morton, John, 1776 (Folder 3.17)
  - Paca, William, 1776 (Folder 3.18)
  - Paine, Robert Treat, 1757 (Folder 3.19)
  - Rodney, Caeser, 1775, 1777 (Folder 3.20)
  - Rush, Benjamin, 1786, 1794, 1810 (Folder 3.21)
  - Rutledge, Edward, 1782 (Folder 3.22)
  - Sherman, Roger, 1786 (Folder 3.23)
  - Smith, James, 1782 (Folder 3.24)
  - Walton, George, 1785 (Folder 3.25)
  - Whipple, William, 1778 (Folder 3.26)
  - Williams, William, 1776 (Folder 3.27)
  - Wolcott, Oliver, 1775 (Folder 3.28)
  - Wythe, George, 1803 (Folder 3.29)
- Series VII: The American Navy
  - Angus, Samuel, 1813 (Folder 1.14)
  - Bainbridge, WM., 1819 (Folder 1.15)
  - Biddle, James, n.d. (Folder 1.16)
  - Broom, C. R., 1816 (Folder 1.17)
  - Coutler, Mifflin, 1831 (Folder 1.18)
  - Crane, WM. M., 1827 (Folder 1.19)
  - Decatur, Mrs. Stephen, 1824 (Folder 1.20)
  - Elliott, Jesse D., 1813, 1827 (Folder 1.21)
  - Farragut, Admiral D.G., 1863 (Folder 1.22)
  - Harrison, Joseph, 1807 (Folder 1.23)
  - Hull, Isaac, 1818, 1829, 1835 (Folder 1.24)
  - List of Stores, 1812 (Folder 1.25)
  - Morris, J., 1819 (Folder 1.26)
  - Petition Signed by 42 Members Of Crew of Guerriere, 1815 (Folder 1.27)
  - Porter, D., 187-, n.d. (Folder 1.28)
  - Rodgers, John, 1822 (Folder 1.29)
  - Rogers, Jno., 1812 (Folder 1.30)
  - Shubrick, E.B., 1823 (Folder 1.31)
  - Smith, Hon. R., 1808 (Folder 1.32)
  - Warrington, Lewis, 1838, 1842 (Folder 1.33)
  - Worden, John L., 1840 (Folder 1.34)
- Series VIII: William Tecumseh Sherman
  - William Tecumseh Sherman, n.d. (Folder 1.34)
- Series IX: Napoleon and His Generals
  - Abrantes, D. — Duchess, 1845 (Folder 1.36)
  - d'Anglas, Boissy, 1818 (Folder 1.37)
  - Bailly, Jean Sylvain- Mayor of Paris, 1789 (Folder 1.38)
  - Berthier, Louis Alexandre -Marshal, 1810 (Folder 1.39)
  - Bertrand, Henry Gratien -General (Folder 1.40)
  - Beurnomville, Pierre -Marshal, n.d. (Folder 1.41)
  - Bonaparte, Napoleon, n.d. (Folder 1.42)
  - Bourbon, Louis de, n.d. (Folder 1.43)
  - Bourgeois, R.- In Battle of Waterloo, n.d. (Folder 1.44)
  - Chaptal, 1808 (Folder 1.45)
  - Chenier, C.H., n.d. (Folder 1.46)
  - Clary, Julia Marie — Queen of Spain, Wife of Joseph Bonaparte, 1813 (Folder 1.47)
  - Damme, Dominique Joseph Van — General, 1813 (Folder 1.48)
  - Desaix, Louis Charles Antoine — General, 1792 (Folder 1.49)
  - Destouches, Philippe Nericault, 1834 (Folder 1.50)
  - Fonquier, Tinville, 1793 (Folder 1.51)
  - Gouvion, Saint Cyr — General, 1817 (Folder 1.52)
  - Le Hefvre, F.G. — General, 1808 (Folder 1.53)
  - Lauriston, Jacques Alexandre — Marquis-General, 1808 (Folder 1.54)
  - Malherbe, Francois de, n.d. (Folder 1.55)
  - Montesquieu, Marquis A.P. — General, 1796 (Folder 1.56)
  - Montholon, Charles Tristan — General, n.d. (Folder 1.57)
  - Murat, Joachim — King of Naples, Cavalry Commander (Folder 1.58)
  - Phillippe, Louis — Duke de Chartres, 1848 (Folder 1.59)
  - Segur, 1782 (Folder 1.60)
  - Unidentified, n.d. (Folder 1.61)
  - Walewska, Count Andrew — Son of Napoleon (Folder 1.62)
- Series X: Civil War
  - Angur, C. C., 1865 (Folder 2.1)
  - Army Pass, 1861, 1865 (Folder 2.2)
  - Banks, N. P., 18-- (Folder 2.3)
  - Barlow, F. S., 1865 (Folder 2.4)
  - Blunt, Jas. G., 1866 (Folder 2.5)
  - Burnside, A. E., 1869 (Folder 2.6)
  - Butler, B. F., 1862 (Folder 2.7)
  - Cameron, Simon, 1885 (Folder 2.8)
  - Casey, Gen'l. Silas, 1865 (Folder 2.9)
  - Cass, Lewis, 1859 (Folder 2.10)
  - Chase, Salmon P., 1864 (Folder 2.11)
  - Cox, J. D., 1864 (Folder 2.12)
  - Curtis, S. R., 1865 (Folder 2.13)
  - Dent, F. T., 1866 (Folder 2.14)
  - Dodge, G. M., 1865 (Folder 2.15)
  - Grant, Ulysses S., 1863 (Folder 2.16)
  - Halleck, H. W., 1863 (Folder 2.17)
  - Hancock, Winfield Scott, 1808 (Folder 2.18)
  - Heintzleman, S. P., 1862, 1863 (Folder 2.19)
  - Herron, F. J., 1866 (Folder 2.20)
  - Hooker, Joseph, 1862 (Folder 2.21)
  - Howard, O. O., 1866 (Folder 2.22)
  - Jackson, Jas. W., 1852 (Folder 2.23)
  - Johnson, R. W., 1863 (Folder 2.24)
  - Lincoln, Abraham, 1862 (Folder 2.25)
  - Logan, John A., 1867, 1868 (Folder 2.26)
  - Lyon, N., 1861 (Folder 2.27)
  - Marcy, R. B., 1862 (Folder 2.28)
  - Martindale, J. H., 1863 (Folder 2.29)
  - McClellan, Geo. B., 1864 (Folder 2.30)
  - Order for Cask Ale, 1865 (Folder 2.31)
  - Paine, Chas. J., 1866 (Folder 2.32)
  - Porter, Fitz John, 1862 (Folder 2.33)
  - Rosencrans, W. S., 1862 (Folder 2.34)
  - Rousseau, L. H., 1866 (Folder 2.35)
  - Sale of Army Mule, 1863 (Folder 2.36)
  - Scott, Winfield, 1861 (Folder 2.37)
  - Sheridan, Phil, 1867 (Folder 2.38)
  - Sherman, William T., 1866 (Folder 2.39)
  - Sickles, Danz, 1867 (Folder 2.40)
  - Stanley, D. S., 1874 (Folder 2.41)
  - Stanton, Edwin M., 1864 (Folder 2.42)
  - Sykes, G. D., 1864 (Folder 2.43)
  - Thomas, G., 1866 (Folder 2.44)
  - Townsend, E. D., 1867 (Folder 2.45)
  - Vanderveer, WM., 1865 (Folder 2.46)
  - Wheaton, Frank, 18-- (Folder 2.47)
- Series XI: English Literature and Art
  - The Barber's Shop Ad, n.d. (Folder 4.1)
  - Blackstone, W., 1766 (Folder 4.2)
  - Burke, Edmund, 1787 (Folder 4.3)
  - Canning, George, 1820 (Folder 4.4)
  - Coledon, 1865 (Folder 4.5)
  - Collingwood, 1807 (Folder 4.6)
  - Cornwills, Barry, n.d. (Folder 4.7)
  - Desaike, Edward, n.d. (Folder 4.8)
  - Dickens, Charles, 1870 (Folder 4.9)
  - Edgeworth, Maria, n.d. (Folder 4.10)
  - Eliot, George, 1858, 1861 (Folder 4.11)
  - Gortchakof, Prince Peter, n.d. (Folder 4.12)
  - Grattar, Henry, 1793 (Folder 4.13)
  - Hook, Theodore, 1856 (Folder 4.14)
  - Hume-Jones, Philip, 1899 (Folder 4.15)
  - Irving, Washington, n.d. (Folder 4.16)
  - James, G. V. R., 1851 (Folder 4.17)
  - Johnson, Samuel, 1782 (Folder 4.18)
  - Key, Francis Scott, n.d. (Folder 4.19)
  - Kipling, Rudyard, n.d. (Folder 4.20)
  - Knowles, Shendac, 1834 (Folder 4.21)
  - Landsar, Sir Edwin, 1869 (Folder 4.22)
  - Lang, Andrew (Folder 4.23)
  - Lardner, Dion, 1834 (Folder 4.24)
  - Lemon, Mark, 1863 (Folder 4.25)
  - Lerch, Mark, 1864 (Folder 4.26)
  - Levis, C., n.d. (Folder 4.27)
  - Lighte, Fred, n.d. (Folder 4.28)
  - Lockhart, J., n.d. (Folder 4.29)
  - Longfellow, Henry W., n.d. (Folder 4.30)
  - Martin, Theodore, n.d. (Folder 4.31)
  - Morgan, Sydney, 1839 (Folder 4.32)
  - Ophir Hall Ticket, n.d. (Folder 4.33)
  - Pepys, Samuel, n.d. (Folder 4.34)
  - Pitt, Harriot, 1769, 1770 (Folder 4.35)
  - Pitt, Hester, n.d. (Folder 4.36)
  - Pitt, William, 1770, 1771 (Folder 4.37)
  - Pluyfair, Lyon, n.d. (Folder 4.38)
  - Proctor, R. W., 1855 (Folder 4.39)
  - Rapell, J. H., n.d. (Folder 4.40)
  - Rogers, Samuel, n.d. (Folder 4.41)
  - Rose, George, 1857 (Folder 4.42)
  - Saffi, A., 1868 (Folder 4.43)
  - Sandars, 1855 (Folder 4.44)
  - Shillen, Mrs., n.d. (Folder 4.45)
  - Stevenson, Robert Louis, 187- (Folder 4.46)
  - Talma, Francois Joseph, 1809 (Folder 4.47)
  - Tennyson, Alfred, n.d. (Folder 4.48)
  - Terquem, P. N., 1885 (Folder 4.49)
  - Thackeray, William M., n.d. (Folder 4.50)
  - Turner, 18-- (Folder 4.51)
  - Unidentified, 1840 (Folder 4.51)
- Series XII: Edmund Burke
  - Burke, Edmund, 1772 (Folder 4.53)
- Series XIII: Robert Browning
  - Robert Browning Letter, 1878 (Folder 2.48)
  - Browning Family Photographs, n.d. (Folder 2.49)
- Series XIV: Robert E. Lee
  - Robert E. Lee, 1854 (Folder 2.50)
- Series XV: Constitution of The United States
  - "We the People of the United States…do Ordain and Establish this Constitution for the United States of America." Printed in 2 columns on 4 numbered pages in Philadelphia by Dunlap and Claypool (Evans, American Bibliography 20817), 1787 (Volume 2)
- Series XVI: Presidents of The United States
  - Album containing letters and documents signed by every United States president from George Washington through Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1796-1929 (Volume 3)
- Series XVII: Robert Louis Stevenson
  - Autograph transcript signed of his poem, "To H.F. Brown,", 18-- (Volume 4)
- Series XVIII: Napoleon and His Family
  - Album containing approximately 10 letters and documents signed by Napoleon Bonaparte and members of the imperial family, including the Empress Josephine and Empress Mari-Louise, 1787?-1816? (Volume 5)
- Series XIX: Koran
  - Manuscript copy of the Koran, approximately 600 leaves, 17-- (Volume 6)